Listen to a talk in a biology class.
In the early 1900s, sea otters, marine mammals that feed on invertebrates including sea
urchins, were nearly wiped out along the United States Pacific Coast by fur hunters.
With otters gone, urchin numbers exploded, destroying kelp forests.
That kelp is a type of seaweed and it's sea urchins favorite food.
This left countless marine species without the protective habitat that kelp forest provided to them.
In 1972, hunting sea otters was banned.
As otters made a comeback, urchin numbers dropped, kelp forest grew back, and biodiversity flourished.
Scientists realized otters were a keystone species, organisms whose impact on ecosystems is far
greater than their numbers suggest.
A similar case occurred in Yellowstone National Park.
Wolves, the park's top predator, had been eradicated.
Populations of elk, a deer-like animal and a favorite prey for wolves, soared
and their huge populations damaged local vegetation, including the Willow
and Aspen trees for which the park had been famous.
In the 1990s, wolves were reintroduced to the park to get the elk population under control.
But the wolves didn't just cut elk numbers, they changed elk behavior.
Afraid of being eaten by wolves, the elk avoided stream side areas where they're especially vulnerable.
This helped Willow and Aspen trees reestablish themselves there,
and the trees brought back Beavers, animals that live in streams
and build dams to create ponds for themselves.
The Beaver dams created habitats for fish, birds and amphibians, a huge cascading effect
because of this other keystone species.